I found that out the... Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Yesterday's דף,
daf, which is for us today's דף, daf, is קי"ד Kuf-Yud-Daled 114.
We're going to have to do a double דף daf on שבת.
Shabbos. We'll maybe we'll get a little bit further today. We pick
up on the משנה. Mishna. So we just had a very juicy
discussion over the last yesterday's דף daf has became two דפים daphim
or whatever because it's so central discussions, one about דינא דמלכותא דינא
Dina D'malchuta Dina and the other about גזל גוי, Gezel Goy,
and you know, obviously we don't have to review those, but very
critical issues that arose there. But the key point there that the
גמרא, Gemara, the משנה Mishna focused on was the somebody has stolen
moneys in their purse or whatever that you're not supposed to change
money with them because either because the owners were not מיאש mi'yaesh
so you're directly taking stolen funds even though it's not exactly sure
which and it's a little fungible there, or because even if the
owners are מיאש, mi'yaesh, you know, it's just seen as as despicable
that's not the right word whatever but you know, inappropriate, unseemly, whatever.
What? You like the word despicable? Okay, anyway, you know, to be
sort of taking it directly from that pouch in which the sort
of stolen things are are saved. So that would be even if
there were יאוש. ye'ush. So that's relevant for this next משנה. Mishna.
Let's take a look at this next משנה Mishna which continues with
the tax collectors. נטלו מוכסין את חמורו, Natlu mochsin es chamoro, so
the tax collectors seized your donkey, okay, in arrears I guess. ונתנו
לו חמור אחר, Venasnu lo chamor acher, but they had they had
like רחמנות rachmanus on you, and they took your nice Cadillac donkey
and they gave you a... what would be another example? A Volkswagen.
Okay. נטלו ליסטים
את כסותו, Natlu listim es kesuso, they took your Armani suit, ונתנו
לו כסות אחרת, venasnu lo kesus acheres, and they gave you Target.
Okay. הרי אלו שלו. Harei elu shelo. Now the thing that they
gave you they seized from somebody else, okay? So can you keep
it? I mean, you know, you don't want to go naked or
whatever, I mean, it's maybe you salvaged something. So yes, you're allowed
to keep it. Why? מפני שכבר נתייאשו מהם. Mipnei shekvar nityashu mehem.
You can assume that the owners were מיאש, mi'yaesh, you know, gave
up hope of getting it back, so it's יאוש ושינוי רשות. ye'ush
v'shinui reshus. Now how's that similar to the idea before when you're
not supposed to take money from their pouch? Okay, so the simplest
sort of resolution which the רשב"א Rashba says is that לכתחילה l'chatchila
versus בדיעבד. b'diavad. Yes, we assume יאוש ye'ush once מוכסין mochsin take
people's stuff, but people are מיאש mi'yaesh from getting it back, whatever
you see about סתם גניבה סתם גזילה, stam g'neiva stam g'zeila, the
tax collectors take your stuff, you're not going to get it back.
And nevertheless to take directly from that pouch of stolen goods לכתחילה
l'chatchila you shouldn't do. But in this case, A, where it's a
little bit מציל מידם, matzil mi-yadam, you know, you sort of are
like salvaging something, and B, it's after the fact, you know, they
gave it to you, so in that case already you are allowed
to keep it. הרי אלו שלו. Harei elu shelo. Yes.
Do you think it's at all interesting that ליסטים listim are in
the same category
as מוכסין, mochsin,
tax collectors?
Right. Thank you for pointing that out. Right.
In other words, that the מוכסין mochsin are גנבים. ganavim. Right. But
no, there's a professional... like I'm a professional, seriously, I'm a professional
thief.
That's a good point. Okay. המציל מן הנהר. Hamatzil min hanahar. Now
that's a case where where there was יאוש ye'ush after some type
of a theft or whatever. But now how about יאוש ye'ush that's
more like a a little mix of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia and
אבידה aveida and the יאוש ye'ush that comes from גניבה g'neiva or
גזילה? g'zeila? המציל מן הנהר מן הגייס ומן הליסטיס Hamatzil min hanahar
min hagayas u'min halistis or ליסטים listim whatever. Somebody who saves an
object that had been swept away by the river, or from a
troops that had seized it, or from bandits, okay, so different cases
of גניבה g'neiva versus אבידה, aveida, but there's יאוש ye'ush and you
went and you jumped into the river and you took it or
you were able to somehow get the bandits to give it to
you on the cheap or something. אם נתייאשו הבעלים הרי אלו שלו.
Im nityashu hab'alim harei elu shelo. If the owners were מיאש, mi'yaesh,
you can keep it. So pretty similar to the previous point that
it's you know that it's sort of after the fact, they're salvaging
something, sort of like being able to get change from the מוכר,
mocher, and then with יאוש ושינוי רשות, ye'ush v'shinui reshus, right, it
raises a question of you לכתחילה l'chatchila being a party to creating
the the שינוי רשות. shinui reshus. You know something is stolen, there's
יאוש, ye'ush, by you taking it you are being מוציא motzi it
מרשות בעלים, me-reshus ba'alim, okay, but nevertheless, like I said, there's an
element here about salvaging, there's certainly could be an aspect of it
being after the fact, and therefore you can keep it. The only
real difference in the משנה Mishna which the גמרא Gemara is going
to focus on is, can you presume יאוש ye'ush or do you
have to know יאוש? ye'ush? In the beginning it spoke about and
the same type of circumstance seems to be described. The beginning describes
ליסטין listin and says you can assume there was יאוש, ye'ush, and
the second circumstance also mentions ליסטין listin and says if there was
יאוש. ye'ush. So that's going to be the question of the גמרא
Gemara like when can יאוש ye'ush be presumed and when does it
have to be established? Yes, Charlie.
This is different from secular law in the case of shipwrecks.
Okay, shipwrecks what?
So a a naval vessel continues to be the property of that
country
even after it's sort of declared as lost and irretrievable.
Right. And there's actually a special federal law a ship... Shipwreck, you
can't, basically it's illegal to go to go diving for treasure.
Yeah, diving for treasure without permission of the... Interesting. Okay. Amrit? How
do you know that?
Charlie knows everything. אמר רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא: Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben
Broka: נאמנת אשה או קטן לומר, Nemenet isha o katan lomar, a
woman or a minor whose testimony normally is not accepted in court,
is believed to say מכאן יצא נחיל זה. Mikan yatza nachil zeh.
That this... oh, did I skip a line? Yes, I did skip
a line. וכן נחילו של דבורים, Vechein nachilo shel devorim, and similarly
a swarm of bees, אם התייאשו הרי אלו שלו. Im hityashu harei
elu shelo. So a swarm of bees like, you know, they... you're
a bee, what's it called, keeper and the bees swarm... an apiary...
and whatever, yeah, they swarm and they go to some other, you
know, they all leave your field and they're going somewhere else. So
yeah, what's the chance you're going to get it back? So if
you're מייאש, miyeiash, that's... now we're really into בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
territory, then somebody else can just take it. Okay, now אמר רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka says נאמנת אשה או
קטן לומר מכאן יצא נחיל זה. Nemenet isha o katan lomar mikan
yatza nachil zeh. Now
let's say you're not מייאש, miyeiash, okay, but there's a question whose
bees are they? You can trust a woman or a minor to
say, "Oh yeah, I saw it leave Reuven's field, I saw them
swarm out." Okay, now the question is: why is that true? Like,
normally we don't accept their testimony, so we'll see about that in
the גמרא. Gemara. ומהלך בתוך שדה חברו, Umehalech betoch sadeh chaveiro, once
we're talking about capturing bees, so again, in case you're not מייאש,
miyeiash, you can cut through your neighbor's yard or go into your
neighbor's yard להציל את נחילו, lehatzil et nachilo, that they're now swarming,
they're in your neighbor's yard, you know, you got to run after
them, you're in hot pursuit, so you're allowed to, you know, to
trespass in order to get it. ואם היזיק, Ve'im hizik, and if
you damage something in the process, משלם מה שהיזיק, meshaleim mah shehizik,
you have to pay what you damaged. Why?
So like, pressing, he needs to like run through his fields with
the...
because then they'll all fly away, they'll escape, whatever.
You mean they're flying so he's not going to catch them? Supposedly
just, you know, nesting.
We're going to get to nesting in a minute. Okay, but here
they're in the process of flying away. All right. אבל לא יקוץ
את סוכו על מנת ליתן את הדמים. Aval lo yikotz et sacho
al menat litein et hadamim. Let's say they rested, they nested, on
a branch in somebody else's yard. So the easiest way to retrieve
them is you cut off the branch and you walk with the
branch back to your yard and they all stay hovering around the
branch. Okay, that you're not allowed to do unless you have his
permission, even if you're planning on paying him for it. Because that's
a direct conscious act of מזיק, mazik, that's not like incidental to
what you're doing. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר
אף קוצץ שפונו ונותן את הדמים. Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka omer af kotzet shapuno venotein et hadamim. No, you are
allowed to do it. Now how you allowed to consciously be מזיק
mazik somebody else to save your own property? You know, is that
a general rule? We're going to see in the גמרא Gemara that
this is a special allowance that they gave for this circumstance.
So you're not allowed to run through his yard and damage it
in the process of cutting off this branch.
No, yes you are, that was the previous thing and then you
pay for what you damage.
See, I would think that like, you know, when they're running away,
okay, you got to get them back now, but they're already nested,
why do you...
oh, I see. Once they're nested, yeah, I assume if there's no
longer any urgency, then you don't have to. Okay, but this also
is not like a general principle that I'm allowed to... I mean,
look, you know, there was an interesting... we had a גמרא Gemara
before מהו להציל עצמו בממון של חברו, mahu lehatzil atzmo bemamon shel
chaveiro, and that was about saving your own life, which is very
strange, like what should ever stand in the way of פיקוח נפש.
pikuach nefesh. But anyway, but here even according to this last opinion,
the גמרא Gemara is going to say it's a special exception by
a swarm of bees. It doesn't mean in general if I think
like, oh, you know, my... yeah, whatever, you know, right, like you
know, my... exactly... well whatever, you know, my car is about to
roll off the cliff and whatever, it's worth twenty thousand dollars, I
can push Michael's car off in front and that will block my
car and his is only worth ten thousand dollars and I'm allowed
to do that to pay him back. Like we don't have a
general rule you can be מזיק mazik somebody else's property to save
your property even if you're intending to pay back. But it's a
special allowance according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka,
you know, for the case of the bees. Yes, just like...
maybe I'm the only one who's not totally expert here, but like
it must be that when a whole hive of bees goes somewhere
else, they all fly in one... Yes, exactly.
Yeah, yeah,
yeah, that clearly they stay in the swarm. They all stay in
the swarm. Because I'm a total expert on that and everything I've
seen on TV indicates that. Okay, so let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. תנא. Tana. Okay, we תנא tana ברייתא. Braisa. אם
נטל מחזיר לבעלים ראשונים. Im natal machzir libe'alim rishonim. Back to the
donkey, exchanging your donkeys. אם נטל מחזיר לבעלים ראשונים. Im natal machzir
libe'alim rishonim.
It says the opposite of our משנה, Mishnah, or it seems to
say that if you actually took a donkey and exchanged for yours,
you have to give it back to the original owners. So the
גמרא Gemara says קסבר, kasavar, so the ברייתא Braisa is of the
opinion ייאוש כדי לא קני, ye'ush kedi lo kani, that the ייאוש
ye'ush alone is not sufficient, ומעקרא באיסורא אתא לידיה, u'meikara b'isura ata
l'yadei,
and originally it's came to your hands in transgression, okay, which basically
means now what does this exactly mean? So רש"י Rashi says, if
you look at רש"י, Rashi, ייאוש כדי שנתיאשו הבעלים ביד מוכס לא
קנה המוכס בייאוש לחודו. Ye'ush kedi shenityashu habe'alim beyad mocher lo kana
hamoches beye'ush lachudo. המוכס Hamoches doesn't get it בייאוש לחודו. beye'ush lachudo.
ולא נתנסת דמיו של שני באיסורא אתא לידיה. V'lo nitnasat damo shel
sheni b'isura ata l'yadei.
So even though it's a ייאוש ye'ush and a שינוי רשות, shinui
reshus, since you were a party to it leaving the owner's control,
you did the שינוי רשות shinui reshus after when you got it
from the tax collector, it was still belonging to the original owner.
Your accepting of it was the one thing that sort of took
it away from the owner. So in that type of case, since
you're a party to it... party to that, you have to return
it. Now, is that really the הלכה? halacha? Is that really the
הלכה halacha that you don't own it if you were a party
to the יאוש ושינוי רשות? yeush v'shinuui reshus? We've never seen that
before. I mean, everything we've learned until now is, you're the, you're
the third party, there's יאוש yeush in the hands of the גנב,
ganav, you receive it, it's yours, you get to keep it. Okay,
so the, so the רשב"א, Rashba, long רשב"א Rashba on this, but
basically what he says is is that this isn't arguing, this is
almost like adding a מידת חסידות. middas chasidus. Like the משנה mishna
says as a legal point, הרי אלו שלו. harei elu shelo. Technically,
you own it. But as the right thing to do, okay, מחזיר
לבעלים הראשונים, machzir l'baalim harishonim, you know, you should, you know, you
know, so, you know, you should give it back to the owner.
You could also even add that the difference here is that it
says אם נטל. im natal. The משנה mishna was, they were נוטל
notel and they gave it to you. You were very passive in
the whole transaction, right? Let's say it was a little different. They
took your donkey and you say to them, look, don't leave me
stranded without a donkey, can I at least have that, you know,
that scraggly donkey over there? And they say fine, take it. So
you actively were the initiator and active, right? That might be different.
But the bottom line is, technically you do own it, but there's
some sense here like the right thing to do at least under
some circumstances is to return it to the owner. Okay, ואיכא דאמרי,
v'ika d'amrei, others say, אם בא להחזיר יחזיר לבעלים הראשונים. im ba
l'hachzir yachzir l'baalim harishonim. If you want to, it's not like you
should, if you want to. מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason?
יאוש קני, yeush kani, that יאוש yeush alone is קונה. koneh. Now
again, one way to read this is, the גנב ganav really fully
owned it, okay. מיהו יאמר, mihu yomar, if you say, אפשי בממון
שאינו שלי, afshi b'mamon she'eino sheli, you know, I don't want to
have anything that somehow had somehow ill-gotten gains or anything that somehow
was a little that's tainted, in that case מחזיר לבעלים הראשונים machzir
l'baalim harishonim you give it back. So again, you could read this
that it's really a debate about יאוש, yeush, right, that like that
whether if the גנב ganav really owned it, the tax collector really
owned it, then there's, you know, technically it's fully yours and then
it's only like a real act of צדקה. tzedaka. Or another way
that some ראשונים rishonim explain this is they're really not asking whether
יאוש yeush is קונה, koneh, they're really sort of asking what's your
degree of responsibility when you are the one that caused it to
leave the owner's, you know, control, the owner's, you know, ownership. So
they both agree, יאוש yeush in the hand of the מוכס, moches,
שינוי רשות shinui reshus in the hands of you that you took
it. Okay, but one just says, well, that leaves you with a
real sense of like a real moral responsibility to return it. You
were the thing that caused it to transition. So where the other
says, no, you know, the fact that it was יאוש yeush in
the hand of the מוכס, moches, that's enough that you don't have
any moral responsibility. Same way you pick up a lost object that
the owner was מיאש, myaiesh, you're allowed to keep it. You take
a גניבה gneivah or גזילה gezeilah after the owner was מיאש, myaiesh,
that doesn't give you any moral responsibility. You want to do it
because you're a צדיק, tzadik, that's a different story. But you know,
it doesn't give you any moral responsibility, okay? So it's very interesting
here, whether are they debating יאוש, yeush, are they debating the degree
of moral responsibility, are they disagreeing with the משנה mishna and the
first opinion is saying you don't really own it or the way
the רשב"א Rashba reads it, everybody is agreeing you really own it,
but there is a question here about the degree of sort of
moral responsibility in this case. Yes.
Joe, we've been learning a lot of גמרא Gemara and I'm really
struck by the, is it accurate to say that the moral responsibility
for acting is often not the basis for the legal standard that's
set? Right? Yeah, Joe, like that's such a striking, yeah,
Ma, that's a very good point. I mean, yeah, we did see
a lot of cases where basically like, you know, the גזלן gazlan
gets to keep all these things and benefits from the whole thing
or whatever, and like the legal stuff seems to like not be
in sync with our moral sensibilities, which doesn't mean that there isn't
a discourse about the moral sensibilities, but the point that you're making
is is to what degree is the sort of legal system some
degree reflecting that or we're really operating on very unrelated principles. It's
a really good point. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: הרי אלו שלו מפני שבעלים נתייאשו. harei elu shelo mipnei shebaalim
nisyashu. So now the גמרא, Gemara, so that was sort of like
the interesting question about can you take it and how much of
a responsibility do you have by being party to the whole, you
know, leaving of the owner's control and being party to that whole
thing. And now we're just going to focus on this issue, a
more narrow issue about when do we assume יאוש yeush occurred and
when do we have to establish that יאוש yeush occurred.
Sense of, sense of, I mean it's presumably the underpinning of this
whole discussion is that it is not typical for them to give
you a bargain, because if it were, then everyone could say, well,
if you just legislate it they just have to give it back
to the first person, no one would ever be מיאש. myaiesh. You
know what I'm saying?
Yeah, but just because, but just because it's a case where it's
done, I mean if they're not constantly, but it's occasionally done. Yeah,
right, I mean they're not constantly swapping donkeys and at the end
of the day they're left with one donkey, you know what I
mean? Every what? Right, I mean obviously every now and then they
give it to somebody. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says: הרי
אלו שלו מפני שהבעלים נתייאשו. harei elu shelo mipnei shebaalim nisyashu. אמר
רב אסי: amar Rav Assi: לא שנו אלא לסטים עובד כוכבים. lo
shanu ela listim oved kochavim.
This is only true about a non-Jewish, you know, bandit that you
assume that the owners are מיאש myaiesh because the first part of
the משנה mishna presumed יאוש. yeush. אבל לסטים ישראל, aval listim Yisrael,
לא, lo, but if you got a nice פרום frum Jewish bandit,
לא, lo, then you're not מיאש. myaiesh. Why? סבר למחר נקיטנא ליה
בדינא. savar l'machar nakitna lei b'dina. Oh, because... the Jewish guy I
can actually step to בית דין, beis din, maybe guilt him into
it, maybe he's more subject to the rule of בית דין, beis
din, so there's less ייאוש, ye'ush, you more hope you'll get it
back when it's a Jewish bandit. Okay. Well,
right, good point. מתיב, masiv, point was the bandits is the only
contradiction for the first half and the second half of the משנה.
Mishnah. מתיב ליה רב יוסף, masiv leh Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav
Yosef challenges, אדרבה, aderaba, the opposite, איפכא מסתברא, ipcha mistabra, the opposite
makes sense. עכו"ם Akum or גוים, Goyim, דדינא בגיסי, de-dina be-geisei, that
phrase, we sort of, we saw this phrase before with arrogance meaning
that basically, and we saw what that meant earlier, like yesterday, that
they will accept even one testimony, you know, one witness, that they
just, you know, more give themselves a lot more latitude to find
somebody guilty. That's what this sort of phrase means. So they're very
willing to find people guilty, לא מייאש, lo miya'esh, you're not מייאש
miya'esh because you figure you know, I can win a case in
a non-Jewish court that I couldn't win in a Jewish court. I
guess, actually, well no, no, this is the least of the issues,
the tax, okay.
עכו"ם... Akum... ישראל, Yisrael, כיון דאמרי מימר מייאש, keivan de-amri meimar miya'esh,
but Jews, since they talk a lot, you're מייאש. miya'esh. I'm sorry,
that's what the word means. Now what does this mean since they
say, you're מייאש? miya'esh? So רש"י Rashi has two explanations. So רש"י
Rashi says first of all it means that they don't enforce their
rule with, they don't actually have the, the, you know, sort of
the weight of the government behind them. They can't use, you know,
a police force to enforce their rule. They can only try to
do it verbally and by putting somebody in חרם. cherem. So you
feel even if I win the case, who knows if the guy's
actually going to listen to בית דין? beis din? Obviously that really
resonates nowadays, right? You know, people go to a בית דין, beis
din, it doesn't like, it's going to be completely unenforced unless people
sign binding arbitration and put the weight of the secular government behind
it. Okay, so one is you don't really believe it's going to
get you anywhere because it doesn't really have the weight of, you
know, force behind it. And the other explanation רש"י Rashi has is,
לשון אחר, lashon acher, דאמרי ליה נגזל, de-amri leh nigzal, מי יימר
כדקאמרת, mi yeimar ked-ka'amrat, they'll just say to the guy, yeah you're
lying, go prove it, which means that it's harder to prove things
in Jewish court, they don't, you know, they don't base on circumstantial
evidence as much. Exactly, exactly. Or bribe the judge or whatever.
Exactly,
yeah, although here it's not mentioning bribing but it is mentioning standards
of evidence. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is saying here, you said
that people are less מייאש miya'esh by Jews because they think Jews
are more subject to the דין, din, it's the opposite. You know,
Jews are more, since Jews means dealing with the Jewish legal system,
you're less, you feel less likely to get it back and you're
more readily מייאש miya'esh as opposed to dealing with the secular system,
you feel that you're more likely to get it back and you're
less likely to be מייאש. miya'esh. Now, you know, I do want
to sort of say that the obvious irony here is that what
it sort of saying is that people feel that, you know, at
least the person feels more justice can be served by going to
the secular system. א', alef, if he wins, he'll actually get to,
the judgment will be acted upon, but ב', beis, you know, while
we're being critical of oh they have low standards of evidence, from
the perspective of the נגזל, nigzal, it's like I'll be able to
actually win my case, you know. So anyway, it's very interesting. Yes.
Yeah, so you see they're using this phrase עכו"ם Akum over וגוים.
v-Goyim. Yeah again, that's a, that's a gloss. That's, what does Steinsaltz
have? Steinsaltz' text reflects the ווילנא ש"ס. Vilna Shas. Do they all
refer to
גוי? Goy?
Every single reference in Steinsaltz is גוי, Goy, גוים.
Goyim. Yeah all this is originally גוי, Goy, yeah.
Yeah, the thing about only one witness in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, the גמרא
Gemara says you only need one witness for a death penalty in
a non-Jewish court.
Oh, in a non-Jewish, right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, okay, אלא, ella, okay, so really so we're going to
say people are more מייאש miya'esh when the Jews are the bandits.
אלא איתמר אסיפא איתמר. Ella itmar asifa itmar. So if this thing
was said that it only applies to non-Jews, it wasn't said by
the רישא reisha where we assume ייאוש, ye'ush, it was said by
the סיפא seifa where we presume that there wasn't ייאוש ye'ush unless
we know otherwise. המציל מן העכו"ם ומן הלסטים, Ha-matzil min ha-Akum u-min
ha-listim, אם נתייאשו הבעלים אין. im nityashu ha-be'alim in. It
says if you rescue from the non-Jew and from the bandits, in
our משנה Mishnah it says המציל מן הנהר או מן הגייס, ha-matzil
min ha-nahar o min ha-gayis, it doesn't say גוים, Goyim, it says
גייס, gayis, או מן הלסטים, o min ha-listim, anyway, but the point
is we're going to read this idea at the end which is
talking about לסטים listim and you presume and you don't presume ייאוש
ye'ush is because it was non-Jewish לסטים. listim. אם נתייאשו הבעלים אין,
Im nityashu ha-be'alim in, only if the owners were מייאש, miya'esh, only
if it's established ייאוש, ye'ush, סתמא לא, stama lo, but the presumption,
the default is with non-Jews there's no ייאוש. ye'ush. Okay. לא שנו
אלא עכו"ם, Lo shanu ela Akum, that's only true about non-Jewish bandits
or גוים. Goyim. משום דדייני בגיסי, Mishum de-dayni be-geisei, because they have
more latitude when they judge, you know. אבל לסטים ישראל, Aval listim
Yisrael, but if it's a Jewish bandit, כיון דאמרי מימר, keivan de-amri
meimar, since again what אמרי מימר amri meimar means, it's only by
words, easy to push off challenges and claims, so it's harder to
win a case. In that case מייאש, miya'esh, they are מייאש. miya'esh.
Okay, so people are more readily מייאש miya'esh by Jewish bandits than
by non-Jewish.
Is there a backhanded compliment?
Yeah, that's what I was saying. Basically means that from the נגלה'ס
Nigleh's perspective justice can more be served in the secular court. You
know, look, when the when חב״ד Chabad lost their case in, you
know, they took it to a דין תורה, Din Torah, the whole
thing about the רבי'ס Rebbe's library or whatever, right, so then of
course what happens when the side loses and you're not, you know,
you're not happy, you so fine, they took it to secular court,
right, you know, so I mean that's always a difficulty too because
you can get a different judgment in secular court, doesn't necessarily mean
more justice is served. But yeah, I mean a lot of people,
you know, they're always saying like you gotta go to a בית
דין, Beis Din, gotta go to בית דין, Beis Din, a lot
of people feel like like A it'll be more enforceable in non-Jewish
court and also people feel that they'll get more justice in it,
you know, which is what the BDA's trying to change that perception
and change some of the reality, but you know, some of that
you see already in this גמרא.
Gemara. You see סאטמאר Satmar רביים Rebbes pursuing each other in secular
court for years. Right, right. There actually are places where בית דין
Beis Din decisions are not enforceable.
Even if they do binding arbitration? Why? Because it violates church/state as
they've decided to ban religious arbitration.
Interesting. We'll have to talk about that more later. Anyway, I think
of one of those cases, I don't remember if it was about
the about the ליובאוויטש Lubavitch library or if it was about the
סאטמאר Satmar which was going on in secular court, but I do
remember the story, at one point the judge sort of, you know,
you have all these like, you know, חסידים Chassidim whatever on both
sides whatever they're saying, the judge looks at them and says like
isn't this something called a desecration of the Divine Name?
So, just yesterday we had the whole חילול השם Chillul Hashem sort
of about. Anyway,
all right. So exactly. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
Okay, so the גמרא, Gemara, where was I? Okay. Okay,
תנן. Tnan. תנן התם. Tnan Hasam. Now we're going to take the
try to analyze this, when do we presume יאוש, ye'ush, when do
we not? Okay, so we taught over there in כלים. Keilim. Okay,
which what does כלים Keilim have to do with it? Well, we're
going to see. עור של בעל הבית, Or shel ba'al habayis, if
you are a homeowner, not a manufacturer, not a store owner, we've
seen this before, and you're just processing your own leathers and you're
processing leather and you're planning on making out of it some type
of a mat or something. מחשבה מטמאתן, Machshavah metama'atan, as soon as
you decide, yeah, it's enough done in the processing, this is good,
I'm going to use it like this as a mat, then it's
defined as a כלי, kli, as a utensil, and whatever and therefore
it can become טמא. tamei. Okay, because when do you know when
is the process done, when is it still not yet finished? Well,
you're you're the owner, your intending it, that defines it's done. ושל
עבדן, Veshel avdan, but if you are the actual tanner, אין מחשבה
מטמאתן. ein machshavah metama'atan. Then when you think it's done doesn't matter,
you know, the customer's always right. What do you it's not about
you, you're going to do if somebody says to you like I
want to use it now, fine, use it now. If somebody says
I want it to go through some more of a process, you're
the customer, you're the owner. So your מחשבה machshavah does not define
this as a כלי. kli. של גזלן אין מחשבה מטמאתן. Shel gazlan
ein machshavah metama'atan. Now, how about if somebody stole a piece of
leather and decided, oh, I'm going to now use this as a
mat? Okay, so if you're a גזלן, gazlan, your
we're going to assume here that once the owners are מיאש, miyaesh,
give up hope of getting it back, since it's under your control,
right, this is the whole thing we've been discussing, the owners technically
own it, you're the one who actually has the actual control over
it. So one of the things that you get from your control
over it, we saw before for example is if you use it
you don't have to pay the owners. Right, but another thing you
get is you sort of can define what it is, you're controlling
it, it's under, you know, you know, you're the one who's actually
in practice using it. So for this הלכה halacha of טומאה וטהרה,
tumah vetaharah, if you decide I'm going to use this as X,
well guess what, that's how it's going to be used. Right now
you're the one with it, you're not the legal owner, but that's
the reality of the things, that that is going to define it.
Okay, so only though if there's יאוש. ye'ush. After יאוש ye'ush the
original owner's actual claim to it and presence is much more tenuous
and that's when your מחשבה machshavah as a גנב ganav or גזלן
gazlan can be meaningful. So the question is when do we assume
there is יאוש ye'ush or not? So it says של גזלן אין
מחשבה מטמאתן. shel gazlan ein machshavah metama'atan. If the guy's a גזלן,
gazlan, אין מחשבה מטמאתן. ein machshavah metama'atan. We have to assume the
owners are not מיאש miyaesh because a גזלן gazlan means it was
a
standup robbery or whatever and a holdup I meant and you presumably
know who the guy is and you hope you can get it
back, you know? אבל של גנב, Aval shel ganav, in the case
of a burglary, and he broke into your house in the middle
of the night and you have no idea who it was, then
you're מיאש. miyaesh. מחשבה מטמאתן. Machshavah metama'atan. Then then you're מיאש miyaesh
and the מחשבה machshavah of the גנב ganav does make it a
כלי. kli. רבי שמעון אומר חילוף הדבר, Rabbi Shimon omer chiluf hadavar,
the exact opposite. של גזלן מחשבה מטמאתן. Shel gazlan machshavah metama'atan. By
a גזלן gazlan your מחשבה machshavah is מטמא. metamei. Why? Because רש״י
Rashi says that you are מיאש miyaesh because you say look, if
this guy is so brazen to just in daylight come and rob
from you or whatever, like I'm never going to catch him, you
know, that's it, I give up hope of ever catching him. אבל
של גנב, Aval shel ganav, you know, but a whatever, a burglar,
okay,
אין מחשבה מטמאתן. ein machshavah metama'atan. Him you him you say oh,
a burglar can get caught. Okay, so fine. Actually, I think that
would be interesting to know the statistics on that, but you know,
it does seem like people that do home burglary, right, like you
know, somehow I get a sense like oh yeah, you know, there's
been a rash of burglaries and then eventually they catch the guy
because there's a certain pattern that happened in Riverdale. Right. But like
somebody actually comes and like steals your car, they say like yeah
forget it, it's never getting back. You know, so I wonder if
there's some statistical truth to that.
So do we go back and like retrace? Is it once it's
been assumed and we say okay we assume יאוש yeiush and then
let's say that the thing is found and then we're trying to
figure out was that actually טמא tamei at a specific time? Do
we go to the owner and say at what point were you
מיאש? miyaiesh?
Right. So the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that a little
bit, meaning whether, you know, if there's a presumption of יאוש yeiush
do we allow our knowledge of the concrete knowledge of facts afterwards
to like override? Right. So that's almost, that's pretty close to what
the גמרא's Gemara going to get to. So let's see where the
גמרא Gemara goes. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר עולא מחלוקת בסתם. Amar Ulla Machlokes b'stam.
So this is exactly the next, almost the next point of the
גמרא. Gemara. This debate of when do we assume יאוש yeiush or
not, גנב ganav or גזלן, gazlan, you know, one way or the
other way, that's only if we don't know
otherwise. אבל בידוע, Aval beyadua, see that Jenna, you're channeling Michael, you're
anticipating the next line of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. But when you
know for a fact, now what he means is you know for
a fact that there was יאוש, yeiush, you know, as opposed to
well we were presuming יאוש yeiush and then we found out for
a fact there wasn't, but presumably it would be the same. When
we actually have the facts, okay, so you know the owner was
מיאש, miyaiesh, דברי הכל יאוש קונה. divrei hakol yeiush koneh. Everybody agrees
if you know there was יאוש, yeiush, there was יאוש, yeiush, end
of story. Okay, this is just a question about the presumptions we
make. רבה אמר בידוע נמי מחלוקת. Rabbah amar beyadua nami machlokes. No,
even if you know the owner was מיאש. miyaiesh. Okay, because what
רבה Rabbah basically says is sort of like we know better than
you or like, you know, you could say you're מיאש miyaiesh but
deep down you still are hoping of getting it back. You know,
you can sort of understand that. Somebody's got their car robbed, that's
it, whatever, I'm never going to see it back, but at some
level they're like still praying, they're still hoping it's going to come
back and they still call up the police like once a month
and ask if there's any progress on the case. Okay, so you
know, so he's saying is that's,
so even if you say you're מיאש miyaiesh in whatever the case
is, גנב ganav or גזלן, gazlan, whatever whichever side you adopt in
this debate, the one who says there's no יאוש yeiush means deep
down there's no יאוש yeiush regardless of what you say. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר ליה אביי לרבה. Amlei Abaye le-Rabbah. So אביי Abaye said
to רבה, Rabbah, לא תפלוג אדעולא, lo tivlog a-de-Ulla, do not disagree
with עולא Ulla that says that when we have concrete knowledge that
would
override. דתניא מסניתין כותיה De-tanya masnisin kevashei because our משנה Mishna teaches
like him. What does our משנה Mishna say? Our משנה's Mishna actually
not our משנה, Mishna, the משנה Mishna there about the leather. It
says משלא נתייאשו הבעלים. mi-shelo nisyashu habaalim.
It says you know that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that a
גנב ganav is not מטמא metamei because the owners haven't been
מיאש. miyaiesh. So טעמא דלא נתייאשו. taama d'lo nisyashu. It sounds because
there's just the absence of an actual concrete יאוש. yeiush. Okay, until
so until there's יאוש yeiush we assume they're not מיאש. miyaiesh. אבל
נתייאשו הבעלים Aval nisyashu habaalim the implication is that if they actually
were מיאש, miyaiesh, הרי הוא שלו, harei hu shelo, then you could
keep it. אמר ליה Amlei he said back to him, no,
אנן מפני שאין יאוש הבעלים מתנינן לה. anan mi-pnei she-ein yeiush habaalim
masnisin le-. When רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says because they haven't been
מיאש, miyaiesh, I don't read it because they haven't, I read it
because there's no meaning to their יאוש, yeiush, which is quite a
big re-read of it. Okay, but it's not like oh by גנב
ganav there's no, it's you know
the מחשבה machshavah doesn't mean anything because they have not yet been
מיאש, miyaiesh, that's how you read it, I read it because they're
never מיאש, miyaiesh, okay, as an objective fact, whatever they say they're
never really
מיאש. miyaiesh. Okay, תנן. tnan. Now so now we're going to try
to prove this question whether the objective knowledge can override the
presumptions. נטלו לסטים חמורו, Natlu listim chamoro, going back to our משנה.
Mishna. Okay, where it says that when they take your donkey we
presume יאוש. yeiush. So מני, mani, who is this going like? אי
רבנן קשיא גזלן, Ee Rabbanan kashya gazlan, if it's the רבנן, Rabbanan,
right, the רבנן Rabbanan say, I keep on getting confused here, the
רבנן Rabbanan say,
גזלן gazlan is not יאוש. yeiush. Okay, but our משנה Mishna we're
presuming that לסטים listim have
a status of גזלן. gazlan. Right, so if it's a case
of so if it's the רבנן, Rabbanan, why are we assuming that
לסטים, listim, you know, is יאוש? yeiush? The רבנן Rabbanan suit that
a גזלן gazlan is not יאוש. yeiush. אי רבי שמעון קשיא גנב.
Ee Rabbi Shimon kashya ganav. No wait, wait, there's two cases. The
מוכס Moches I think we're assuming
is the גזלן gazlan and the לסטים listim we're assuming is the,
hold on I get confused.
What does רש"י Rashi say?
מוכס Moches רש"י Rashi says is גזלן, gazlan, לסטים listim is גנב.
ganav. So the מוכס Moches is the גזלן gazlan clearly, he does
it out in the open. Why are we assuming a bandit is
a גנב? ganav? I mean the גמרא Gemara earlier spoke about the
fact that a bandit goes and hides afterwards, so the fact that
after he does the theft he goes into hiding somehow makes him
a גנב. ganav. That's the assumption of the גמרא. Gemara. So the
גמרא Gemara assumes that our משנה Mishna is talking about both a
גזלן gazlan and a גנב ganav and the first part of the
משנה Mishna says that we presume יאוש. yeiush. So who is that
going like? אי רבנן קשיא גזלן, Ee Rabbanan kashya gazlan, if it's
the רבנן Rabbanan then we don't understand why we'd presume יאוש yeiush
by a גזלן. gazlan. אי רבי שמעון קשיא גנב, Ee Rabbi Shimon
kashya ganav, and by רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we don't understand why
we'd presume it by a גנב. ganav. בשלמא לעולא דאמר בידוע קוני
הכל Bishlama le-Ulla d'amar beyadua konei hakol according to עולא Ulla that
says when we know there's יאוש yeiush then everybody agrees, הכא נמי
בידוע ודברי הכל, hacha nami beyadua vedivrei hakol, here too could be
that we know. Of course even that's not a good... The answer
because the משנה mishnah says we presume יאוש. yei'ush. It doesn't say
we know יאוש, yei'ush, right? But anyway, אלא לרבא, ela leRava, but
according to רבא, Rava, דאמר בידוע נמי מחלוקת, de'amar beyadua nami machlokes,
that even when there's known יאוש, yei'ush, so that we'll never have
a case at one buddy that that both a גנב gannav and
a גזלן gazlan it works, right? Because there's always one person that's
saying for one it works and for the other it doesn't. So
the גמרא Gemara says המאני, hamanni, who is this going like? לא
רבנן ולא רבי שמעון. lo Rabbanan velo Rabbi Shimon. So the גמרא
Gemara says דליסטים מזוין ורבי שמעון היא. dilis'tas m'zuyan veRabbi Shimoni. No,
it's going by armed bandits, okay? And therefore armed bandits presumably do
it more out in the open and they don't go into hiding
afterwards, so they're another type of a גזלן. gazlan. So the משנה
mishnah is really talking about two types of a גזלן gazlan and
it's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and that's why there's a presumption of
יאוש. yei'ush. The גמרא Gemara says אי הכי היינו גזלן, ee hachi
hainu gazlan, so why are you saying a second case? We already
mentioned מוכס, mochas, which is a גזלן, gazlan, just so funny, a
מוכס mochas is automatically a גזלן. gazlan. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says תרי גווני גזלן. srei gavnei gazlan. Yeah, we're talking about
two scenarios of a גזלן: gazlan: the tax collector גזלן gazlan and
the armed bandit גזלן. gazlan. All right. תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear, okay? הגנב והגזלן והאנס והקדש הקדשן ותרומתן תרומה, hagannav vehagazlan
veha'anas vehekdesh hekdeshan utrumasan truma,
whether a גנב gannav or a גזלן gazlan or an אנס, anas,
which רש"י Rashi says is somebody basically that forces you to sell
and pays you for it, okay,
all these cases we presume יאוש yei'ush and if they הקדיש makdish
the object, it's like יאוש ושינוי השם, yei'ush veshinui hashem, if they
make it תרומה truma that works because again, once they're in control
and the owner is מיאש, m'ya'ish, so they have a lot of
de facto ownership and over it. ומעשרותן מעשר. uma'asrosan ma'aser. Okay, anyway,
but it means that all those cases we assume יאוש. yei'ush. המאני,
hamanni, who is that going like?
Wait, so you said a מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveira another,
okay,
that might be, but it doesn't mean that as a legal transaction
it didn't take effect. אי רבנן קשיא גזלן אי רבי שמעון קשיא
גנב. ee Rabbanan kashya gazlan ee Rabbi Shimon kashya gannav. Again,
who does that work like? Why don't we why do we presume
it both by גנב gannav and a גזלן, gazlan, if it's either
one or the other? בשלמא לעולא דאמר בידוע קני, bishlama leUlla de'amar
beyadua kani, according to עולא Ulla that says when it's known everyone
agrees, הכא נמי בידוע ודברי הכל. hacha nami beyadua vedivrei hakol. Here
too, could be you know there was יאוש. yei'ush. Of course, okay,
so then it would just it's a little funny because it seems
like part of the point is to say that we can presume
יאוש, yei'ush, but fine, we would read it, there's no presumption of
יאוש, yei'ush, we know there's יאוש. yei'ush. Okay, אלא לרבא דאמר בידוע
נמי מחלוקת, ela leRava de'amar beyadua nami machlokes, but according to רבא
Rava who says that even when we know they debate, so according
to it'll always be either one or the other, when do you
ever have both? So גמרא Gemara says המאני לא רבנן ולא רבי
שמעון. hamanni lo Rabbanan velo Rabbi Shimon. So גמרא, Gemara, הכא נמי
דליסטים מזוין. hacha nami delis'tas m'zuyan. Oh right, when it says גנב,
gannav, it doesn't really mean גזלן, gazlan, it really means an armed
bandit, okay? ורבי שמעון היא, veRabbi Shimoni, so and it's רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon who says גזלן gazlan is יאוש. yei'ush. אי הכי היינו
גזלן, ee hachi haynu gazlan, so we're already saying גזלן. gazlan. No,
תרי גווני גזלן, srei gavnei gazlan, two types of robbers. Of course
that's even a weaker answer because here it doesn't just call it
ליסטים, listes, it labels him as a גנב. gannav. So you're saying
even though we're labeling him as a גנב, gannav, halachically his status
is a גזלן gazlan and that's why there is יאוש. yei'ush. Obviously
a very hard read of this ברייתא. Braisa. ואיבעית אימא, ve'ibayis eima,
so now the גמרא Gemara realizes perhaps the forced nature of this
read, so it gives another answer. ואיבעית אימא המנאיתן רבי היא, ve'ibayis
eima hamnisan Rabbi hi, this is רבי, Rabbi, דתניא רבי אומר אמר
גנב כגזלן. detanya Rabbi omer amar gannav kegazlan. He actually says that
a גנב gannav is like a גזלן gazlan and they both have
the same הלכה. halacha. Now the question is which way? We assume
never יאוש yei'ush or we always assume יאוש? yei'ush? So the גמרא
Gemara is going to say דקיימא לן, dekaimalan, we're going to conclude
a little bit as the דף daf continues,
כגזלן דרבי שמעון, kegazlan deRabbi Shimon, that what it means is they're
both the same and there's always יאוש. yei'ush. So since רבי Rabbi
says there's always יאוש yei'ush by a גנב gannav and a גזלן,
gazlan, even if we would say so then that's why all of
these Tannaitic sources are assuming that there's always יאוש. yei'ush. Okay, so
there's a question about when do we presume יאוש, yei'ush, and then
B, there's the position of רבא Rava that claims actually it's not
just question of presumption, maybe we even ignore what the owner is
saying because we sort of think that like objectively we know deep
down whether there is or not יאוש, yei'ush, yes.
So when a stock swindler gives a makes a big donation to
ישיבה, yeshiva, it actually takes effect and you can keep it.
Yeah, but that's a separate conversation, that was more yesterday too about
the צדקה. tzedakah. Okay, גופא רבי אומר אומר אני, gufa Rabbi omer
omer ani, let's take a look at this statement of רבי. Rabbi.
רבי Rabbi says I say גנב כגזלן, gannav kegazlan, they're the same.
איבעיא להו, Ibaya lehu, כגזלן דרבנן קאמרת, kegazlan derabbanan kamrei, like the
Rabbis' גזלן, gazlan, דלא קני, velo kani, and we presume no יאוש,
yei'ush, או דילמא כגזלן דרבי שמעון קאמרת, odelma kegazlan deRabbi Shimon kamrei,
like רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon גזלן, gazlan, וקני, vekani, we presume there
is יאוש? yei'ush? Okay, so we know we're going to say B.
תא שמע נטלו מוכסין חמורו ta shema natlu mochasin chavaro etc. Okay,
so again back to our משנה mishnah that talks about גזלן, gazlan,
the מוכס, mochas, and the גנב, gannav, the ליסטים, listes, and it
presumes יאוש yei'ush in both cases. המאני אי רבנן קשיא גזלן אי
רבי שמעון קשיא גנב. hamanni ee Rabbanan kashya gazlan ee Rabbi Shimon
kashya gannav. So it doesn't work either רבנן Rabbanan nor רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon because it assumes it presumes יאוש yei'ush in both cases.
אי אמרת בשלמא רבי כגזלן דרבי שמעון קאמר, ee amart bishlama Rabbi
kegazlan deRabbi Shimon kamar, if רבי Rabbi says that both גנב gannav
is like the רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon גזלן gazlan there's always
יאוש yei'ush וקני המאני רבי היא, vekani hamanni Rabbi hi, so then
this is רבי, Rabbi, it assumes that there's יאוש yei'ush in both
cases. משום הכי קני. mishum hachi kani. אלא אי אמרת כגזלן דרבנן
קאמר, ela ee amart kegazlan derabbanan kamar, but if you're saying like
the Rabbis' גזלן gazlan that there's never יאוש yei'ush ולא קני המאני,
velo kani hamanni, who is this going like? לא רבי lo Rabbi
who would say there's never
יאוש, yei'ush, ולא רבי שמעון ולא רבנן velo Rabbi Shimon velo Rabbanan
that says it's either one or the other. So no, הכא במאי
עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, so it's certainly like rehashing the other thing
but now through a different lens. הכא במאי עסקינן דלית ליה מצוין
ורבי שמעון היא. hacha b'mai askinan d'leis leh m'zuyan v'Rabbi Shimon hi.
It's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's talking about armed bandits, armed bandits
are like a גזלן, gazlan, so it's all different types of גזלן.
gazlan. That's why it's יאוש. yeush. אי הכי ei hachi says the
גמרא, Gemara, היינו גזלן, hainu gazlan, then why say it? We already
say גזלן. gazlan. תרי גווני גזלן, trei gavnei gazlan, no, it's two
types of גזלן.
gazlan. מצוין m'zuyan is like the most brazen, like I'm going to
give it back and everything, forget it.
Exactly. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, let's try again, again it's a
ברייתא braita we recorded earlier. הגנב והגזלן והגזבנות הקדש הקדש קומתן תרומה,
haganav v'hagazlan v'hagizbanos hekdesh hekdesh kumosan truma, again גנב ganav and גזלן
gazlan and אונס oness you presume יאוש yeush and therefore they can
be מקדיש maqdish etc. So מעשרתן מעשר maserosan maser מני, mani, who
is this going like? אי רבנן קשיא גזלן. ei Rabbanan qasha gazlan.
If it's the רבנן, Rabbanan, we don't understand why גזלן gazlan we
presume יאוש. yeush. אי רבי שמעון קשיא גנב, ei Rabbi Shimon qasha
ganav, for according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we don't understand why
we presume יאוש yeush by a גנב. ganav. אי אמרת בשלמא גנב
כגזלן דרבי שמעון קאמר, ei amrat bishlama ganav k'gazlan d'Rabbi Shimon ka-amar,
if רבי Rebbe is saying that there's always יאוש, yeush, the גנב
ganav is like the גזלן gazlan of רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
ומשום הכי קני u-mishum hachi kani then you understand why this presumes
יאוש yeush in both cases.
אלא אי אמרת כגנב כגזלן דרבנן, ela ei amrat k'ganav d'gazlan d'Rabbanan,
but if it's like the רבנן Rabbanan גזלן gazlan there's never יאוש,
yeush, הא מני, ha mani, who is this going like? How come
it presumes יאוש yeush in both cases? So מתיבי Meitivi the same
answer, דליסטים מצוין ורבי שמעון היא. d'listis m'zuyan v'Rabbi Shimon hi. No,
it's an armed bandit, גנב ganav doesn't mean גנב, ganav, it really
means armed bandit, it really means גזלן. gazlan. אי הכי היינו גזלן,
ei hachi hainu gazlan, we already said גזלן. gazlan. תרי גווני גזלן,
trei gavnei gazlan, two types of גזלן. gazlan. Fine. Okay, אמר ליה,
amar lei, we said the same thing twice. Yes, but we did
it as once we went through it to try to debate רבה
Rabba and אביי Abaye whether when you know there's יאוש yeush does
that override our presumption? And then we sort of went through oh
well it seems like it must or else how come we're equating
גנב ganav and גזלן? gazlan? And the answer was no, no, ליסטים
מצוין. listis m'zuyan. So then we're going through it with the same
with a different question. רבי, Rebbe, is רבי Rebbe saying that there's
always יאוש? yeush? Let's prove it from these cases. You know the
same way before we were saying let's prove known יאוש yeush works
from these cases, here we're saying let's prove that the רבי's Rebbe's
position is there's always יאוש yeush from these cases. And the answer
in both scenarios is always the same. No, maybe it's only in
the גזלן gazlan case and it's ליסטים מצוין. listis m'zuyan. So yes,
it's rehashing it but trying to prove a different point. Okay, תא
שמע, ta shma, so now we're going to try to do it
from a different way. דמתני רבי לרבי שמעון בריה, d'masnei Rebbe l'Rabbi
Shimon brei, רבי Rebbe taught to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon his son,
לא דבר, lo davar, remember going back to the משנה mishna in
the beginning of the פרק perek when it said that when you
have to return an object, the father died, the sons have to
return it
if it is דבר שיש בו אחריות, davar sheyesh bo achrayus, which
normally means land, and רבי Rebbe taught רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon his
son, לא דבר שיש בו אחריות ממש, lo davar sheyesh bo achrayus
mamash, we don't literally mean land, אלא אפילו פרה וחורש בה וחמור
אחריה, ela afilu parah v'choresh bo v'chamor acharayiv, even if it's a
cow that you're plowing with or donkey that you're leading, if it's
an object that publicly is being used and it's known to be
גזילה, gezeila, חייבין להחזיר chayavin l'hachzir they have to return it מפני
כבוד אביהם mipnei kevod avihem because of honor to their father. So
that means though technically they own it, right? The only reason they're
returning it is because of their father's honor. Why do they technically
own it? So טעמא מפני כבוד אביהם, ta'ama mipnei kevod avihem, remember
the משנה mishna starts what does the first משנה mishna talk about,
a גזלן gazlan or a גנב? ganav? I'll give you a hint,
if you don't know look at the very top of your page
in big letters. Okay, הגוזל ומאכיל. hagezel u'ma'achil.
Right.
So why are we presuming יאוש yeush and the kids own it
and it's only an issue of כבוד? kavod? It must be that
רבי Rebbe assumes that with a גזלן gazlan there's יאוש. yeush. Okay,
טעמא מפני כבוד אביהם, ta'ama mipnei kevod avihem, it's honor of their
father. הא לאו כבוד אביהם ha lav kevod avihem if it's not
for that לא, lo, then they do not have to return it,
so they really own it because of יאוש ושינוי רשות. yeush v'shinui
reshus. שמע מינה רבי גזלן כרבי שמעון קאמר, shma mina Rebbe gazlan
k'Rabbi Shimon ka-amar, you see רבי Rebbe holds a גזלן gazlan like
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon there is יאוש, yeush, and therefore when he
says a גנב ganav is a גזלן gazlan it means that there's
always יאוש. yeush. שמע מינה shma mina that's a good proof and
that's of course the easiest way to read the משנה mishna and
the ברייתות braitos that assume there's יאוש yeush by a גנב ganav
and a גזלן gazlan if not this ליסטים מצוין listis m'zuyan idea
but just no רבי Rebbe assumes there's always יאוש. yeush.
By the way, I thought it was interesting that he said לא
אחריות ממש, lo achrayus mamash, does that mean that
these מטלטלין mitaltelin can be leaned or we don't mean leans in
this case?
No we don't mean leans in this case. Right. אמר רב יוסף
amar Rav Yosef now back to the now next part of the
משנה mishna the swarm of bees. Okay, וכן נחילה של דבורים. v'chen
nechila shel devorim. Okay, that escapes if you know there's יאוש yeush
whatever. מאי וכן, mai v'chen, הכא דאמר, hacha d'amar, אפילו נחילה של
דבורים דתקון דרבנן הוא, afilu nechila shel devorim d'tikun d'rabanan hu, even
when it comes to bees where the very ownership of bees is
only rabbinic, because there's a question like how do you pick up
a bee and actually take possession of it? Now תוספות Tosafot says
he doesn't understand it, okay, if you look at תוספות Tosafot if
you
say דתקונה d'tikuna let's read the last line of the
גמרא. Gemara. דתקון דרבנן בעלמא הוא, d'tikun d'rabanan b'alma hu, or some
have the גירסא דתקון בעלמא הוא, girsah d'tikun b'alma hu, it's just
a rabbinic establishment that you're considered the owner, דקני ליה, d'kani lei,
אפילו סתמא נמי מיאש. afilu stam nami meyaesh. In that case since
you only really own it rabbinically, we're just going to presume יאוש,
yeush, we're not going to wait to hear that you're מיאש. meyaesh.
קא משמע לן, kama shma lan, no, מימר צריכא דבעינא ליה, meimar
tzricha d'ba'ina leh, no, we're only going to say that somebody can
take it if we know the owners were מיאש, meyaesh, we're not
going to presume יאוש. yeush. Now תוספות Tosafot doesn't understand why you
can't own bees. really take possession of these. If you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, he says that דרבנן דעלמא תיקנו
ליה, d'rabbanan d'alma tiknu leh, תוספות, Tosafot, משום דרכי שלום, mishum darkei
shalom, כמו יוני שובך, k'mo yonei shovach, just like for ways of
peace, just like the pigeons, like they're because, you know, how do
you really take possession? They come from the wild. So תוספות Tosafot
says, ותימא דאמאי לא קני להו מדאורייתא בהגבהת הכוורת, v'teima d'amai lo
kanei lehu m'deoraita b'hagbahat hachaveret, just take up the whole beehive. Okay
now, of course, by picking up the beehive you're not really picking
up the bees; the bees are sort of flying on their own
in the beehive, but I guess I don't know if they're asleep,
you're picking them up? If they're lying on the floor of the
beehive? And anyway, exactly. Anyway,
so תוספות Tosafot doesn't really understand why you can't own really own
bees.
Well, how's that different than pulling a mule by a by rein?
There but understand, there your power, no, it's not just you're not
touching it. If the bees are flying around, just because you're lifting
up the hive and but
the bees are just caught inside. I don't...
Yeah, but they're flying with you. Your energy is not being transferred
to the bees and making the bees move. Your energy is just
moving the hive, and the bee is choosing to move along with
the hive.
As opposed to the mule that's not...
No, you're pulling it. Your energy is... Whatever. Okay. Anyway, that's the
way bees work. They're not...
And it doesn't... whatever. תוספות Tosafot doesn't... you're just echoing תוספות, Tosafot,
so you don't understand why it doesn't work. We're moving on. We're
moving on. אמר יהודה בן ברוקא המתייאש שלא לומר, Amar Yehuda ben
Bruka hamitya'esh shelo lomar, a woman or a minor can say it
left this guy's field. So המשנה haMishna asks, אשה וקטן בני עדות
נינהו, isha v'katan bnei edut ninhu, since when can they give testimony?
Now I should point out that in the Ashkenazi Middle Ages, when
it came to women, first of all, in Ashkenaz in the Middle
Ages, in the times of תוספות Tosafot or whatever, were very much
empowered and business women and dealt in whatever commerce and the whole
thing. So there really became an issue about accepting their testimony in
court around business issues and other types of issues. Like, I mean,
in the time when women were would never leave the house or
whatever, so maybe there was it was less of a of a
need to sort of expand the parameters, right? You know, except something
like this: they happen to see somebody running out. Anyway, in the
time of the of the ראשוני אשכנז, Rishonei Ashkenaz, there was a
whole way of that in which they essentially
accepted testimony of women, and the way they did it was saying,
well, it's not technical עדות, edut, it's more like נאמנות, ne'emanut, it's
more like circumstantial. If somebody says it, it's most likely it's good
it's good evidence that it's true. It's not formal testimony. Okay, but
anyway, but you should be aware that there was this sort of
ways of expanding this. But the גמרא Gemara here is prior to
that and is saying like, since when do we accept the testimony
of women or children? So the גמרא Gemara says,
הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהיו בעלים מרדפין אחריהן. hacha b'mai askinan k'gon
shehayu be'alim mirdafin achareihen. Okay, no, no, no, there's other corroborating evidence.
The owners were running after them, you know, Charlie was running after
his bees, "Hey, my bees escaped!" And, okay, maybe Charlie just he
sees that it was my bees and it's a good opportunity to
pretend that they're his; he's very smart and quick and kind of
sees it like that. So it's not a hundred percent proof just
because he's running after them, but it's pretty good
evidence. ואשה וקטן משיחין לפי תומן, v'isha v'katan mesichin l'fi tuman, and
the woman and the child, they're not like doing a formal act
of testimony, because then maybe always, because then again if you're sort
of using this as circumstantial evidence, if somebody is just talking like
in innocence, that's what משיח לפי תומן mesiach l'fi tuman means, and
is not being conscious that their testimony is being used, there's maybe
almost like a more presumption, you know, that they're telling the truth.
Of course, you could say the opposite, right? You could say that,
you know, people talk about a lot of things without really knowing.
If you're going to give testimony in court, you're going to be
really be certain. But as a general rule, the גמרא Gemara understands
that if somebody is just משיח לפי תומו, mesiach l'fi tumo, talking
in all innocence, then there's a larger likelihood that they're not lying
and that what they're... of course, the difference still between lying and
being accurate. But anyway, ואשה וקטן משיחין לפי תומן, v'isha v'katan mesichin
l'fi tuman, and they're just talking, you know, they're just gossiping or
chatting, ואומר מכאן יצא נחיל זה, v'omer mikan yatza nachil zeh, and
they're saying, "Oh my God, did you see that swarm of bees
that left Charlie's whatever? Yeah, oh my, I saw them fly out;
that was a terrible thing," or whatever. So now you've got the
circumstantial evidence plus the משיח לפי תומן, mesiach l'fi tuman, so you
combine those two things and, again, it's not formal עדות, edut, but
it's good, you know, corroborating pieces of evidence to make to create
that presumption. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar leh Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina
said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ולאו, v'lav, are you telling me
that we do not trust the testimony of a woman or a
minor? והרי נחיל של דבורים משיח לפי תומו הוא. v'harei nachil shel
dvorim mesiach l'fi tumo hu. So... wait a minute, did I skip
lines? Yes, I'm sorry. משיחין לפי תומן. Mesichin l'fi tuman. אמר רב
אשי אין משיח לפי תומו כשר אלא לעדות אשה בלבד. Amar Rav
Ashi ein mesiach l'fi tumo kasher ela l'edut isha bilvad.
So he rejects this. No, when do we allow sort of the
innocent talk of women and minors to be used as evidence? That's
only for עדות אשה. edut isha. Now, עדות אשה edut isha רש"י
Rashi sometimes says means testimony that a woman is believed for, which
makes it a little tautologous. Okay, we believe a woman for testimony
a woman is believed for. What it does mean is also specifically
testimony that a woman's husband has died. Like, you actually hear, you
know, that this woman's husband hasn't returned from France for the last
two years and you have some visitors from France and they're just
and they're And they're just chatting and they're just saying, "Oh my
God, remember that funeral we had for that visitor, what was his
name again? Oh yeah, you know, Frank Smith or whatever, you know,
he died in this tragic thing," and they're just talking about it
and all of a sudden the woman says "That's my husband," right?
So that's the case of where you would trust them, there חכמים
Chachamim were particularly very lenient to in order because of עגונה agunah
issues to establish that this woman's husband had died. Okay, so that's
the only time you believe מסיח לפי תומו mesi'ach lefi tumo not
for דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, and even with corroborating evidence. So אמר
ליה amar lei רבינא Ravina to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, Ravina said
to Rav Ashi, "and no, are you telling me that's not, that
we don't ever believe women and children outside of that case? והרי
מחיל של דבורים, V'harei mechil shel devorim, what about back to our
משנה, mishnah, the swarm of bees מסיח לפי תומו הוא, mesi'ach lefi
tumo hu, and that's presumably a case where they're just like מסיח
לפי תומו, mesi'ach lefi tumo, right? Or how else do you explain
why we believe them?" So he said no, שאני מחיל של דבורים
דקנין דרבנן הוא. shani mechil shel devorim dekinyan derabbanan hu. As we
already sort of laid the groundwork for this statement a minute ago,
no, there the Rabbis are more prepared to believe because it's not
real, because nobody really owns bees anyway. Okay, my son would be
very happy, like he says, you don't own a pet, right? You
adopt a pet. Okay, nobody owns animals, so I'm teasing. They don't
say that by all animals. You own cows, you own sheep, bees
you don't own anyway. So since nobody really can own bees, they're
more prepared to believe women and children, but it would not be
a general thing. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says אפילו afillu right,
so לא, lo, are you telling me it would not work by
some type of a biblical thing, you know, that would have some
biblical implications? דאמר D'amar רב יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר amar שמואל, Shmuel,
Rav Yehuda said in the name of Shmuel, מעשה באדם אחד שהיה
מסיח לפי תומו, ma'aseh b'adam echad shehayah mesi'ach lefi tumo, there was
a case about somebody that was just talking in all innocence ואומר
זכורני כשאני תינוק, ve'omer zachorni keshe'ani tinok, "I remember when I was
a child ומורכב על כתיפו של אבא," umurkav al keteifo shel abba,
you know, that my father sort of had me, you know, go
on his, on his shoulders והוציאני מבית הספר, vehotzi'ani mibeit hasefer, and
he'd take me out of school והפשיטוני את כתנתי, vehipshituni et kutaniti,
and he stripped me from my tunic והטבילוני לאכול בתרומה, v'hitbiluni leechol
betarumah, and then he dumped me in the מקוה, mikvah, and then
he would say "now you can eat תרומה," terumah, לערב la'erev "tonight
you can eat תרומה." terumah. רב חנינא מסייע ביה רב חנינא Rav
Chanina Mesaya bei Rav Chanina ended that what the guy was also
saying is וחבריי בדילו ממני vechaverai badilu mimenni and my friends, my
chums, like because I guess he's a school kid, were keeping their
distance from me והיו קורין אותי יוחנן אוכל חלות, vehayu korin oti
Yochanan ochel chalot, stay away from that Yochanan who eats חלות, chalot,
presumably because they don't want to be מטמא metamei him. Couldn't be
too much fun to be a kid if that's what your friends
are saying. Anyway, so he's just sort of remembering, what a weird
story I remember from my childhood. Okay, now by the way this
is particularly interesting because, you know, this is like helping himself, right?
He's sort of, and it's not like, it's like, you know, I've
heard stories about somebody sort of saying things like, "yeah, I remember
my whole thing, seeing my grandfather's grave, it had this weird thing
with the fingers on it, or something, whatever." You know, here it's
like he's saying אוכל תרומה, ochel terumah, אוכל טהרות. ochel tahorot. Nevertheless
it's considered to be מסיח לפי תומו mesi'ach lefi tumo even though
it helps himself, and allow us to establish that he is a
כהן, kohen, והעלו רבי לכהונה על פיו vehe'alu Rabbi lekehunah al piv
and Rabbi used this to establish that he was a כהן. kohen.
So you see, and this is something that he remembers from his
childhood. By the way, what's interesting is, you could say, "but now
he's an adult." You see that it's not just you can't do
the act of testifying when you're a child, you can't even testify,
again there are some exceptions to the rules, but there are cases
where you can, but as a rule, you can't even testify to
things you witnessed as a child. Okay, so ah, look you see
מסיח לפי תומו mesi'ach lefi tumo works and this is presumably biblical
implication. So the גמרא gemara says no, בתרומה דרבנן, bitrumah derabbanan, no
it's only rabbinic implications. Nowadays, it's what they're saying nowadays, all תרומה
trumah is דרבנן, derabbanan, there's no דאורייתא de'oraita implication nowadays about being
a כהן. kohen. I mean, if there is a דאורייתא de'oraita it's
only to be מחמיר, machmir, right, you know, about becoming טמא tamei
and so on. So the גמרא gemara says, והא כדי דאורייתא לא
v'ah kaddi de'oraita lo are you still going to tell me that
דאורייתא de'oraita there isn't an impl- we wouldn't trust מסיח לפי תומו?
mesi'ach lefi tumo? Now by the way, notice here that the גמרא
gemara is dropping the whole idea of corroborating evidence, right? You could
have said with corroborating evidence and in something that anyway is just
דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, property issues, where you could understand we have
more latitude, right, than status issues. But the גמרא gemara is now
focusing on pure מסיח לפי תומו, mesi'ach lefi tumo, okay? אהא Aha
כי אתא רב דימי אמר רב חנא קרטיגנא ki ata Rav Dimi
amar Rav Chana Kartigna so when Dimi came from ארץ ישראל eretz
Yisrael he said in the name of רב חנא קרטיגנא Rav Chana
Kartigna from Carthage, right? Okay. ואמרי לה רב אחא קרטיגנא משתעי V'amrei
lei Rav Acha Kartigna mishtayei or רב אחא קרטיגנא Rav Acha Kartigna
was just telling over the following story. מעשה בא לפני רבי יהושע
בן לוי Ma'aseh ba lifnei Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi ואמרי לה מעשה
בא לפני רבי v'amrei lei ma'aseh ba lifnei Rabbi a story either
came to Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi or Rabbi, בתינוק אחד שהיה מסיח
לפי תומו betinok echad shehayah mesi'ach lefi tumo a certain child that
was just chattering in innocence and presumably he was saying this even
as a child. אני ואמי נשבינו לבין הגוים Ani v'immi nishbeinu l'vein
hagoyim "me and my mother we were taken captive among some non-Jews,"
יצאתי לשאוב מים yatzati lisho'av mayim "I went out to draw water"
דעתי על אמי da'ati al immi "I was constantly thinking about my
mother", right, afraid that she would be taken advantage of. So basically
meaning like I never left her out of my sight or if
I did leave her out of my sight I never left her
out of my, you know, being attending to, making sure that nothing
was happening. ללקט עצים Lelaket etzim to gather wood דעתי על אמי
da'ati al immi I was thinking about my mother. And so, and
so, and so, and therefore implicit in all of that, telling that
story is that the mother was not raped. So והשיאה ר' על
פיו לכהונה vehesi'ah Rebbi al piv likhunah and therefore Rebbi allowed her
to marry a כהן, kohen, okay, and we don't assume that she
was raped. Now again this is particularly interesting because it's a מסיח
לפי תומו mesi'ach lefi tumo that helps yourself, right? So how much
is it לפי תומו? lefi tumo? And nevertheless we believe it, even
though again it seems to have a דאורייתא de'oraita implication, so the
גמרא Gemara says no, בשבויה הקלו, bishvuya hikilu, that's only by cases
of a captive woman that we don't know for sure she was
raped, that's a דרבנן derabbanan concern, again that's not a biblical concern.
So the upshot of this גמרא Gemara is you do not rely,
yeah,
ironically they're not asking the woman.
Right. Well that maybe they assume is not לפי תומו, lefi tumo,
but they're asking the קטן, katan, they're sort of putting woman and
קטן katan in the middle, and presumably the woman herself wouldn't be
as much לפי תומו. lefi tumo. Okay, what's, so what the גמרא
Gemara concludes is that we only trust מסיח לפי תומו mesi'ach lefi
tumo for דרבנן derabbanan issues. But the problem
is
there's a difference between standard issues of status etc. and so many
of these cases where helping yourself as opposed to the way the
גמרא Gemara framed it, it was a מסיח לפי תומו mesi'ach lefi
tumo that you were completely a third and uninvested party in it
and there was corroborating evidence, right? So it's not so clear with
that combination of those two it couldn't work even דאורייתא. de'oraita. Pure
מסיח לפי תומו, mesi'ach lefi tumo, particularly if it's helping yourself, fine,
that doesn't work out, it only works in דרבנן, derabbanan, right? But
it's not so clear what happens when it's not helping yourself and
there's other corroborating evidence. So this for example comes up by the
whole debate of the question about, you know, trusting a non-Jew to
taste food that some טריפה treifa stuff got mixed up, can you
taste any of the טריפה treifa food? Okay, so there's different scenarios.
One is the exact opposite of מסיח לפי תומו, mesi'ach lefi tumo,
he's a chef, he knows that you want, that it matters what
he says, but there sort of it's like similar like there's always
two sides to it, but because he knows how much his reputation
is at stake, you'd actually believe him more. But the other scenario
is just, you know, you're out there with your friend and you're
eating something and he says to you, you know, oh well you
know how does that taste? and you say too good, really, like
you know, can you, does it taste buttery? Or whatever, you know
just a conversation. Okay, so anyway, so he's innocent. So the question
is: can you trust that in order to determine if there was
some טריפות treifus mixed up or whatever? And it's a whole debate
of the פוסקים. poskim. And some say well no, if taste is
a דאורייתא de'oraita concern, right, if taste of טריפה treifa food is
a דאורייתא de'oraita concern, which is a debate in itself, then you
can't trust a non-Jew מסיח לפי תומו. mesi'ach lefi tumo. And they
quote this גמרא: Gemara: if it's a דאורייתא de'oraita you can't trust.
But then others try to say like no, there's other corroborating evidence;
first of all if he says he can't taste it and the
next thing you do is you're going to put it in your
mouth and you're going to taste it, you know, he can be
discovered in two seconds to have like misre-, so anyway, so that
becomes a whole interesting discussion of how much is this an absolute
rule that you cannot trust מסיח לפי תומו mesi'ach lefi tumo in
cases where there's other factors, where it's not benefiting the person himself,
and so on.
That's the basis for a long אשכנזים Ashkenazim and ספרדים. Sefardim.
Yes, yes, but not particularly about that issue, but yes, yes it
does. Okay, אבל aval let's just finish the משנה. Mishnah. אבל לא
יקוץ את סוכו, aval lo yakotz et sukho, but you cannot cut
off the branch in order to bring the bees back to you
unless the guy permits you to. Okay, תניא, tanya, we learned a
ברייתא, beraita, ר' ישמעאל בנו של ר' יוחנן בן ברוקה Rebbi Yishmael
beno shel Rebbi Yochanan ben Beroka אומר, omer, תנאי בית דין הוא.
tenai beit din hu. In general yes, you can't damage somebody's property
even to reimburse him just to save your own property. But here
the court stipulated, okay, שיהא יורד לתוך שדה חבירו וקוצץ סוכו של
חבירו להציל נחילתו. she'yehei yored letokh sedeh chaveiro vekotzetz sukho shel chaveiro
lehatzil nechilato. You can go down into his field, cut off the
branch, in order to save your swarm of bees. ונוטל דמי סוכו
מתוך נחילתו של חבירו. venotel demei sukho mitokh nechilato shel chaveiro.
And then the owner of the field can get himself reimbursed from
liter-, like lit-, it says from within, by paid back from the
swarm of the guy's bees, which doesn't mean you have to give
him bees, but it just means since you're getting all this benefit
obviously you have to reimburse him. Okay, okay, ותנאי בית דין הוא
vtenai beit din hu and similarly, okay, so maybe it is not
just limited to bees, other scenarios as well, ששופך יינו ומציל דבשנו
של חבירו. sheshofekh yeino umatzil devashno shel chaveiro. ונוטל דמי יינו מתוך
דבשנו של חבירו. venotel demei yeino mitokh devashno shel chaveiro. Let's say
I see that Charlie's honey is spilling and, and, and honey is
worth a lot more than wine, and the only thing I have
to catch it with is my barrel of wine. So I can
pour out my barrel of wine, save Charlie's honey, and then Charlie
will have to pay me back. ותנאי בית דין הוא vtenai beit
din hu you know, the loss of my wine, מפרק עציו וטוען
פשתנו של חבירו. mefarek etzav vto'en pishtano shel chaveiro. My donkey is
carrying wood, yours is carrying flax, flax is much more expensive, your
donkey is collapsing, if we don't get that flax back it's going
to get ruined. So I get rid of my wood and I
take off the flax, okay. ונוטל דמי עציו מתוך פשתנו של חבירו.
venotel demei etzav mitokh pishtano shel chaveiro.
And I can get the guy now to pay me back. שכך
התנה יהושע לישראל את הארץ. shekakh hitnah Yehoshua lYisrael et ha'aretz.
This was like a stipulation that everybody implicitly agrees to. So the
question is if things somewhat broaden, but what should be pointed out
is in the last Last two cases, okay, Charlie is not being
מזיק mazik me, I am willingly choosing to sacrifice my thing, okay,
and then I'm expected to get paid back, okay, that's maybe different,
right? That maybe is more generic. If I want to, if I
want to push my five thousand dollar piece of junk car in
front of yours to save your car from being damaged, maybe I
can get reimbursed, that's my choice. But that doesn't mean you can
do it and expect to pay me back. So it is an
interesting question about what are the parameters, it is being somewhat broadened,
okay, one imagines it's not just limited to wine and to honey
and what do you call it and flax, right, it is more
more broadened, but how much does it depend on who's doing it,
who's making the choice, what the other person is saying, some of
those parameters are not clear.